The Short User Manual

This user manual contains information about how to download Tor, how to use it, and what to do if Tor is unable to connect to the network. If you can't find the answer to your question in this document, email help@rt.torproject.org.

សូមសម្គាល់ថាយើងមិនកំពុងផ្ដល់ការគាំទ្រលើមូលដ្ឋានដែលបានជ្រើស, ហើយយើងទទួលបានអ៊ីមែលជាច្រើនរៀងរាល់ថ្ងៃ។ មិនចាំបាច់អារម្មណ៍ទេ ប្រសិនបើយើងមិនត្រឡប់ថយក្រោយផ្លូវត្រង់។

តើ Tor ដំណើរការរបៀបណា

Tor ជាដំណើរការធ្យូនែលនិម្មិតដែលអនុញ្ញាតអ្នកធ្វើឲ្យសុវត្ថិភាព និងភាពឯកជនរបស់អ្នកប្រសើរឡើងលើអ៊ីនធឺណិត។ Tor ដំណើរការដោយផ្ញើចរាចរណ៍របស់អ្នកតាមរយៈម៉ាស៊ីនមេចៃដន្យបី (ដូចដែលបានស្គាល់ជា ការបញ្ជូនត) នៅក្នុងបណ្ដាញ Tor , មុនពេលចរាចរណ៍ត្រូវបានផ្ញើចេញទៅកាន់អ៊ីនធឺណិតជាសាធារណៈ។

រូបភាពខាងលើបង្ហាញពីការរុករករបស់អ្នកសម្រាប់តំបន់បណ្ដាញផ្សេងៗគ្នាលើ Tor ។ ម៉ូនីទ័រពណ៌បៃតងបង្ហាញការបញ្ជូនត នៅក្នុងបណ្ដាញ Tor ខណៈពេលពាក្យគន្លឹះបីបង្ហាញប្លង់នៃការអ៊ិនគ្រីបរវាងអ្នកប្រើ និងការបញ្ជូនបន្តនីមួយៗ។

Tor នឹងធ្វើឲ្យចរាចរណ៍របស់អ្នកដើមអនាមិក, ហើយវានឹងអ៊ិនគ្រីបអ្វីគ្រប់យ៉ាងរវាងអ្នក និងបណ្ដាញ Tor របស់អ្នក។ Tor នឹងអ៊ិនគ្រីបចរាចរណ៍របស់អ្នកផងដែរនៅក្នុងបណ្ដាញ Tor , ប៉ុន្តែវាមិនអាចអ៊ិនគ្រីបចរាចរណ៍របស់អ្នករវាងបណ្ដាញ Tor ទិសដៅចុងក្រោយរបស់វា។

If you are communicating sensitive information, for example when logging on to a website with a username and password, make sure that you are using HTTPS (e.g. https://torproject.org/, not http://torproject.org/).

របៀបទាញយក Tor

កញ្ចប់ដែលយើងបានផ្ដល់អនុសាសន៍ទៅអ្នកប្រើច្រើនបំផុតគឺ Tor Browser Bundle។ កញ្ចប់នេះមានកម្មវិធីអ៊ីនធឺណិតដែលបានកំណត់រចនាសម្ព័ន្ធជាមុន ដើម្បីសុវត្ថិភាពការរុករកអ៊ីនធឺណិតតាមរយៈ Tor, ហើយមិនទាមទារការដំឡើងឡើយ។ អ្នកទាញយកកញ្ចប់, យកប័ណ្ណសារចេញ ហើយចាប់ផ្ដើម Tor ។

មានវិធីពីរផ្សេងគ្នាពីរក្នុងការទទួលយកកម្មវិធី Tor ។ អ្នកអាចរកមើល តំបន់បណ្ដាញគម្រោងរបស់ Tor ហើយទាញយកវា ឬអ្នកអាចប្រើ GetTor, កម្មវិធីឆ្លើយតបអ៊ីមែលស្វ័យប្រវត្តិ។

របៀបទទួលយក Tor តាមអ៊ីមែល

ដើម្បីទទួលបាន English Tor Browser Bundle សម្រាប់ Windows, ផ្ញើអ៊ីមែលទៅ gettor@torproject.org ដោយប្រើ windows ក្នុងតួសេចក្ដីសារ។ អ្នកអាចទុកប្រធានបទទទេ។

អ្នកអាចស្នើ Tor Browser Bundle សម្រាប់ Mac OS X បានផងដែរ (សរសេរ macos-i386), និងលីនុច (សរសេរ linux-i386 សម្រាប់ប្រព័ន្ធ 32-bit ឬ linux-x86_64 សម្រាប់ប្រព័ន្ធ 64-bit)។

ប្រសិនបើអ្នកចង់បានកំណែដែលបានបកប្រែនៃ Tor, សរសេរ ជំនួយ ជំនួស។ អ្នកនឹងទទួលបានអ៊ីមែលដោយមានសេចក្ដីណែនាំ និងបញ្ជីភាសាដែលមាន។

ចំណាំ៖ Tor Browser Bundles សម្រាប់លីនុច និង Mac OS X ធំជាង ហើយអ្នកមិនអាចទទួលបានកញ្ចប់ទាំងនេះជាមួយ Gmail, Hotmail ឬគណនី Yahoo ។ ប្រសិនបើអ្នកមិនទទួលបានកញ្ចប់ដែលអ្នកចង់ទទួលបានទេនោះ, ផ្ញើអ៊ីមែលទៅ help@rt.torproject.org យើងនឹងផ្ដល់ឲ្យអ្នកនូវបញ្ជីតំបន់បណ្ដាញដែលត្រូវប្រើ។

Tor សម្រាប់ទូរស័ព្ទទំនើប

អ្នកអាចទទួលបាន Tor នៅលើឧបករណ៍ Android របស់អ្នកដោយដំឡើងកញ្ចប់ដែលមាន Orbot។ សម្រាប់ព័ត៌មានបន្ថែមអំពីរបៀបទាញយក និងដំឡើង Orbot, សូមទស្សនា តំបន់បណ្ដាញគម្រោង Tor ។

We also have experimental packages for Nokia Maemo/N900 and Apple iOS.

របៀបផ្ទៀងផ្ទាត់ដែលអ្នកមានកំណែត្រឹមត្រូវ

មុនពេលដំណើរការ Tor Browser Bundle, អ្នកគួរតែប្រាកដថាអ្នកមានកំណែត្រឹមត្រូវ។

កម្មវិធីដែលបានទទួលមានជាមួយឯកសារដែលមានឈ្មោះដូចគ្នាជាកញ្ចប់ និងផ្នែកបន្ថែម .asc ។ ឯកសារ .asc នេះជាហត្ថលេខា GPG ហើយអនុញ្ញាតឲ្យអ្នកផ្ទៀងផ្ទាត់ឯកសារដែលអ្នកបានទាញយកដោយជាក់លាក់មួយដែលយើងបានផ្ដល់ឲ្យអ្នកទទួលបាន។

មុនពេលអ្នកផ្ទៀងផ្ទាត់ហត្ថលេខា អ្នកត្រូវទាញយក ហើយដំឡើង GnuPG ៖

Windows: http://gpg4win.org/download.html
Mac OS X: http://macgpg.sourceforge.net/
Linux: Most Linux distributions come with GnuPG preinstalled.

សូមចំណាំថាអ្នកត្រូវកែផ្លូវ និងពាក្យបញ្ជាដែលបានប្រើខាងក្រោម ដើម្បីទទួលបានវា ដើម្បីចូលដំណើរការនៅលើប្រព័ន្ធរបស់អ្នក។

Erinn Clark signs the Tor Browser Bundles with key 0x63FEE659. To import Erinn's key, run:

      gpg --keyserver hkp://keys.gnupg.net  --recv-keys 0x63FEE659

    

បន្ទាប់ពីនាំចូលពាក្យគន្លឹះ, ផ្ទៀងផ្ទាត់ថាស្នាមផ្ដិតមេដៃរបស់អ្នកត្រឹមត្រូវ៖

      gpg  --ស្នាមផ្ដិតមេដៃ 0x63FEE659

    

អ្នកគួរតែទស្សនា៖

      pub   2048R/63FEE659 2003-10-16
      Key fingerprint = 8738 A680 B84B 3031 A630  F2DB 416F 0610 63FE E659
uid                  Erinn Clark <erinn@torproject.org>
uid                  Erinn Clark <erinn@debian.org>

uid                  Erinn Clark <erinn@double-helix.org>
sub   2048R/EB399FD7 2003-10-16

    

ដើម្បីផ្ទៀងផ្ទាត់ហត្ថលេខានៃកញ្ចប់ដែលអ្នកបានទាញយក, ដំណើរការពាក្យបញ្ជាដូចខាងក្រោម៖

      gpg --verify tor-browser-2.2.33-2_en-US.exe.asc tor-browser-2.2.33-2_en-US.exe

    

The output should say "Good signature". A bad signature means that the file may have been tampered with. If you see a bad signature, send details about where you downloaded the package from, how you verified the signature, and the output from GnuPG in an email to help@rt.torproject.org.

Once you have verified the signature and seen the "Good signature" output, go ahead and extract the package archive. You should then see a directory similar to tor-browser_en-US. Inside that directory is another directory called Docs, which contains a file called changelog. You want to make sure that the version number on the top line of the changelog file matches the version number in the filename.

របៀបប្រើ Tor Browser Bundle

After downloading the Tor Browser Bundle and extracting the package, you should have a directory with a few files in it. One of the files is an executable called "Start Tor Browser" (or "start-tor-browser", depending on your operating system).

នៅពេលអ្នកចាប់ផ្ដើម Tor Browser Bundle, ដំបូងអ្នកត្រូវមើលការដំឡើង Vidalia និងរបៀបតភ្ជាប់អ្នកទៅបណ្ដាញ Tor ។ បន្ទាប់មក អ្នកនឹងឃើញកម្មវិធីអ៊ីនធឺណិតបញ្ជាក់ថាអ្នកកំពុងប្រើ Tor ឥឡូវនេះ។ វាត្រូវបានធ្វើដោយការបង្ហាញ https://check.torproject.org/ អ្នកអាចរុករកអ៊ីនធឺណិតឥឡូវនេះតាមរយៈ Tor ។

សូមចំណាំថាវាមានសារៈសំខាន់ដែលអ្នកប្រើកម្មវិធីអ៊ីនធឺណិតមានកញ្ចប់នេះ, ហើយមិនមានជាកម្មវិធីអ៊ីនធឺណិតផ្ទាល់ខ្លួនរបស់អ្នក។

តើត្រូវធ្វើអ្វី នៅពេល Tor មិនតភ្ជាប់

Some users will notice that Vidalia gets stuck when trying to connect to the Tor network. If this happens, make sure that you are connected to the Internet. If you need to connect to a proxy server, see How to use an open proxy below.

ប្រសិនបើការតភ្ជាប់អ៊ីនធឺណិតកំពុងដំណើរការ, ប៉ុន្តែ Tor នៅតែមិនអាចតភ្ជាប់ទៅបណ្ដាញ, ព្យាយាមអនុវត្តដូចខាងក្រោម; បើកផ្ទាំងពិនិត្យ Vidalia , ចុចលើ កំណត់សារ ហើយជ្រើសផ្ទាំង កម្រិតខ្ពស់ ។ វាអាច Tor នឹងមិនអាចតភ្ជាប់ដោយសារ៖

នាឡិកាប្រព័ន្ធរបស់អ្នកបិទ៖ សូមប្រាកដថាកាលបរិច្ឆេទ និងពេលវេលានៅលើប្រព័ន្ធរបស់អ្នកត្រឹមត្រូវ ហើយចាប់ផ្ដើម Tor ឡើងវិញ។ អ្នកត្រូវធ្វើសមកាលកម្មនាឡិកាប្រព័ន្ធរបស់អ្នកជាមួយម៉ាស៊ីនមេពេលវេលាអ៊ីនធឺណិត។

You are behind a restrictive firewall: To tell Tor to only try port 80 and port 443, open the Vidalia control panel, click on Settings and Network, and tick the box that says My firewall only lets me connect to certain ports.

កម្មវិធីកុំចាត់មេរោគរបស់អ្នកត្រូវបានទប់ស្កាត់ Tor ៖ សូមប្រាកដថាកម្មវិធីកុំចាត់មេរោគរបស់អ្នកមិនរារាំង Tor ពីការបង្កើតការតភ្ជាប់បណ្ដាញ។

ប្រសិនបើ Tor នៅតែមិនដំណើរការ, វាប្រហែលជាកម្មវិធីផ្ដល់សេវាកម្មអ៊ីនធឺណិតរបស់អ្នក (ISP) កំពុងទប់ស្កាត់ Tor ។ ជាញឹកញាប់វាអាចត្រូវបានដំណើរការជាមួយ Tor bridges, បានលាក់ការបញ្ជូនតដែលមិនមានភាពងាយស្រួលក្នុងការទប់ស្កាត់។

If you need help with figuring out why Tor can't connect, send an email to help@rt.torproject.org and include the relevant parts from the log file.

របៀបស្វែងរក bridge

ដើម្បីប្រើ bridge, ដំបូងអ្នកត្រូវកំណត់ទីតាំងមួយ; អ្នកអាចរុករកតាម bridges.torproject.org, ឬអ្នកអាចផ្ញើអ៊ីមែលទៅ bridges@torproject.org ។ ប្រសិនបើអ្នកផ្ញើអ៊ីមែល, សូមប្រាកដថាអ្នកសរសេរ get bridges នៅក្នុងតួសេចក្ដីអ៊ីមែលរបស់អ្នក។ ប្រសិនបើមិនផ្ញើអ៊ីមែល, អ្នកនឹងមិនទទួលបានចម្លើយតបឡើយ។ ចំណាំថាអ្នកត្រូវផ្ញើអ៊ីមែលនេះពី gmail.com ឬ yahoo.com address ។

ការកំណត់រចនាសម្ព័ន្ធអាសយដ្ឋាន bridge ច្រើនជាងមួយនឹងធ្វើឲ្យការតភ្ជាប់ Tor របស់អ្នកមានស្ថេរ, នៅក្នុងករណី bridges មួយចំនួនមិនអាចទៅដល់។ គ្មានការធានា bridge ដែលអ្នកកំពុងប្រើឥឡូវនេះនឹងដំណើរការនៅថ្ងៃស្អែកនោះទេ, ដូច្នេះអ្នកគួរតែទម្លាប់ធ្វើបច្ចុប្បន្នបញ្ជីbridges របស់ជាញឹកញាប់។

របៀបប្រើ bridge

Once you have a set of bridges to use, open the Vidalia control panel, click on Settings, Network and tick the box that says My ISP blocks connections to the Tor network. Enter the bridges in the box below, hit OK and start Tor again.

How to use an open proxy

If using a bridge does not work, try configuring Tor to use any HTTPS or SOCKS proxy to get access to the Tor network. This means even if Tor is blocked by your local network, open proxies can be safely used to connect to the Tor Network and on to the uncensored Internet.

The steps below assume you have a functional Tor/Vidalia configuration, and you have found a list of HTTPS, SOCKS4, or SOCKS5 proxies.

Open the Vidalia control panel, click on Settings.
Click Network. Select I use a proxy to access the Internet.
On the Address line, enter the open proxy address. This can be a hostname or an IP Address.
Enter the port for the proxy.
Generally, you do not need a username and password. If you do, enter the information in the proper fields.
Choose the Type of proxy you are using, whether HTTP/HTTPS, SOCKS4, or SOCKS5.
Push the OK button. Vidalia and Tor are now configured to use a proxy to access the rest of the Tor network.

Frequently Asked Questions

This section will answer some of the most common questions. If your question is not mentioned here, please send an email to help@rt.torproject.org.

Unable to extract the archive

If you are using Windows and find that you cannot extract the archive, download and install 7-Zip.

If you are unable to download 7-Zip, try to rename the file from .z to .zip and use winzip to extract the archive. Before renaming the file, tell Windows to show file extensions:

Windows XP

Open My Computer
Click on Tools and choose Folder Options... in the menu
Click on the View tab
Uncheck Hide extensions for known file types and click OK

Windows Vista

Open Computer
Click on Organize and choose Folder and search options in the menu
Click on the View tab
Uncheck Hide extensions for known file types and click OK

Windows 7

Open Computer
Click on Organize and choose Folder and search options in the menu
Click on the View tab
Uncheck Hide extensions for known file types and click OK

Vidalia asks for a password

You should not have to enter a password when starting Vidalia. If you are prompted for one, you are likely affected by one of these problems:

You are already running Vidalia and Tor: For example, this situation can happen if you installed the Vidalia bundle and now you're trying to run the Tor Browser Bundle. In that case, you will need to close the old Vidalia and Tor before you can run this one.

Vidalia crashed, but left Tor running: If the dialog that prompts you for a control password has a Reset button, you can click the button and Vidalia will restart Tor with a new random control password. If you do not see a Reset button, or if Vidalia is unable to restart Tor for you; go into your process or task manager, and terminate the Tor process. Then use Vidalia to restart Tor.

For more information, see the FAQ on the Tor Project website.

Flash does not work

For security reasons, Flash, Java, and other plugins are currently disabled for Tor. Plugins operate independently from Firefox and can perform activity on your computer that ruins your anonymity.

Most YouTube videos work with HTML5, and it is possible to view these videos over Tor. You need to join the HTML5 trial on the YouTube website before you can use the HTML5 player.

Note that the browser will not remember that you joined the trial once you close it, so you will need to re-join the trial the next time you run the Tor Browser Bundle.

Please see the Torbutton FAQ for more information.

I want to use another browser

For security reasons, we recommend that you only browse the web through Tor using the Tor Browser Bundle. It is technically possible to use Tor with other browsers, but by doing so you open yourself up to potential attacks.

Why Tor is slow

Tor can sometimes be a bit slower than your normal Internet connection. After all, your traffic is sent through many different countries, sometimes across oceans around the world!